Love usually leads to trouble.
Inherent Vice is a drama, mystery, comedy film directed by Paul Thomas Anderson.
In Los Angeles at the turn of the 1970s, drug-fueled detective Larry "Doc"
Sportello investigates the disappearance of an ex-girlfriend.
Larry "Doc" Sportello, played by Joaquin Phoenix.
Lt. Det. Christian F. "Bigfoot" Bjornsen, played by Josh Brolin.
Coy Harlingen, played by Owen Wilson.
Shasta Fay Hepworth, played by Katherine Waterston.
Deputy D.A. Penny Kimball, played by Reese Witherspoon.
Sauncho Smilax, Esq., played by Benicio del Toro.
Inherent Vice is a 2014 American neo-noir black comedy crime film written for the screen,
co-produced, and directed by Paul Thomas Anderson, based on the 2009 novel by Thomas Pynchon.
The ensemble cast includes Joaquin Phoenix, Josh Brolin, Owen Wilson, Katherine Waterston, Eric Roberts,
Reese Witherspoon, Benicio del Toro, Jena Malone, Maya Rudolph, Martin Short and Joanna Newsom.
The film follows Larry "Doc" Sportello, a well-intentioned but fumbling stoner, hippie, and private investigator embroiled in the criminal
underworld of 1970 Los Angeles, investigating three cases linked by the disappearance of his ex-girlfriend and her wealthy new boyfriend.
Anderson's adaptation of Inherent Vice had been in development since 2010,
and is the first Pynchon novel to be adapted for the screen.
Anderson was previously inspired by Pynchon's novel V.
while writing the screenplay for The Master (2012), and would go on to
loosely adapt Vineland into One Battle After Another (2025).
It is Anderson's second collaboration with Phoenix, following The Master, and involves a number of his other recurring collaborators,
including producers Daniel Lupi and JoAnne Sellar, cinematographer Robert Elswit, editor Leslie Jones, and composer Jonny Greenwood.
Inherent Vice premiered at the New York Film Festival on October 4, 2014, and began a limited
theatrical release in the United States on December 12, 2014, by Warner Bros.
The film received positive reviews from critics, with many praising the performances,
costumes, and screenplay, but some criticizing the complicated plot.
It was nominated for several awards, including Best Adapted Screenplay and Best Costume Design at the 87th Academy
Awards, and Best Actor – Motion Picture Musical or Comedy for Phoenix at the 72nd Golden Globe Awards.
The National Board of Review named it one of the ten best films of the year.
Some critics said that Inherent Vice has the makings of a cult film.
In 2016, it was voted the 75th best film since 2000 in
the BBC's international critics' poll.
The film explores themes of california, based on
novel or book, boat, detective, 1970s.
The tone is lighthearted and dark and emotional.